Suzanne cook writer who's really going
to whose work is really going to take us
into the very highest levels of not only
post conventional but post formal
cognitive development or what she would
call ego development it's important to
understand that
Suzanne cook Reuter is looking at
meaning making in in that process one of
the factors in meeting in meaning-making
is cognitive development as we have been
talking about it but there are other
factors in meaning making that are not
so evident in other models and so she
looks at the role for example of time
awareness how we spatial eyes and
temporal eyes our understanding among
other other factors that she includes
now some of you may be familiar with
this illustration that we see and that's
the spiral of development and so the
idea here is has cognitive development
as we develop as people through these
stages the development is driven by a
tension between two different poles and
so for example in some systems the
tension is between agency or
individualism and communion or
collectivism and the idea is that at
each one of these stages you oscillate
the individual oscillates between
gem tech' bias or being more agenting or
individual to being more communal and
then more authentic in our individual
and more communal or group oriented and
that there's this back and forth at each
level of development that resolves the
tension in a kind of an oscillating way
so at stage one there is a gent ik bias
at stage two communal it gives you the
impression then that every other level
there's more in common there's something
in common certainly with respect to this
polarity at every other level then at
the level just before and so this tends
to give the every other stage some basis
for commonality and so they're cooked
greater has emphasized or identified
some polarities that are especially
significant to in driving the
conventional levels to post conventional
stages of ego development and so this is
a relative to our theme today this is
obviously a dialectical movement in
development that is part of her model
and so the polarities that she
emphasizes are part and whole self and
other
outer and inner and by extension
objective and subjective short-term and
linear versus long-term and nonlinear
and absolute versus relative and so she
sees that these play out on all of these
polarities play out at each stage of
development and they play out in
different ways at each stage of
development so we see not only a
dialectical aspect to the model of
cognition but it's pointing to something
that is stage specific itself in
development so for example she outlines
the development itself of the concept of
opposites
and so at the early conventional stage
for example she characterizes the
understanding of OPS's opposites as just
one thing this there is not even there's
no there's no even not that it's just
this and only a person at higher
development looking in can see that that
is only part of an opposite but in this
case in very early stage there's only
this so it's it's not dialectical at all
at the next stage it turns into this but
at the conventional stage the way that
opposites are held is this or that and
an argument for example could have an
either-or form prior to this you
wouldn't have an either-or form at the
pluralist stage the way the operatives
are looked at or described are both end
concept of mutuality and so we see that
the progression of the way categories or
opposite categories are actually talked
about or handled or the form of an
argument of explanation that a person
has develops over time this is a little
different than the sequence of the
development or the profound shift that
we saw in the dualistic mind in the
evolutionary story because now we're
working with the
electical mind itself the fundamental
structure consciousness and we see that
this dualism that's inherent in it
itself develops over the lifetime of an
individual now past here these are all
conventional stages and so now we get
into the post conventional ways of
construing or like pros come into a
conception and opposites and they get
more a little more complicated so we
have both and and either-or so these are
both both included as appropriate so
what's appropriate for the situation
either of both end or an either or or
and of both end either/or so the modes
of dealing with opposites become much
more they're more more modes or more
choices available and this concept of
healthy systems need to be inclusive as
of all these options and so it's a very
high stage it's a post conventional
stage and we will look further it's
associated with the autonomous stage
beyond this are two other stages that
are very very rare and this one stage is
called the construct aware stage and
these are an awareness that the
opposites arise as a function
of language and that opposites are not
in the world or the situation but they
are in the mind and how it creates
represents the world or the conditions
how it represents that in language or
other symbolic representation so the
constructor where stage there's this
huge ship so you no longer are that
concerned with how to negotiate how to
negotiate opposites okay so in all of
these you see a progressive
effectiveness in complexification of how
to negotiate opposites but if the
construct aware phase what opposites are
really what I pose that are really okay
you're trying to get this out comes to
the forefront okay now this is a very
very very big shift and so that the
construct aware person understands that
the framing of reality through language
creates this condition or situation of
opposite
and then that then turns over to one
highest stage that is described which is
the unitive stage and in this case there
is an awareness of what she calls the
dance of duality and non-duality and so
we're far cry from looking at this this
but that this or that either or the
these two here are much much much richer
and more complex forms of appreciating
opposite and instead of negotiating with
opposites now which is sort of in this
dance with this this experience of an
expression of this dance and so those
are the ways that Suzanne could brighter
looks at polarities and opposite in both
the model of the drivers of development
and also in the ways that as an
individual develops what their concept
of opposites and how they handle
opposites changes over time